

Curriculum Vitae for Robert Hagala

Personal information

Address: Hagelundveien 5 E-mail: rh@xal.no

0963 Oslo Phone: +47 992 46 527

Born: 12 June 1991 Nationality: Norwegian

Summary

I hold a PhD in astrophysics from the University of Oslo, where my field of research was large scale numerical N-body simulations. Through my research and work I have developed expertise in numerical modeling, statistical and visual analysis of big data sets, signal processing, pattern recognition, high- and low-level programming, and code optimization. I have learned many complex concepts in science and technology, and demonstrated my ability to understand and combine many areas of knowledge. I consider myself an analytical, adaptive, and openminded person with the ability to work highly individually and quickly adapt to unforeseen circumstances. I am experienced with having a holistic overview of a project, while at the same time being able to focus on details.

Technical skills

Languages Python, FORTRAN, C/C++, Java, PHP, SQL, R, Clojure

Frameworks Numpy, Scipy, Flask, Matplotlib, MPI/OpenMP

Tools Git, Unix, Windows, Jupyter Notebook, OpenOffice, LATEX, MS-

SQL, TimescaleDB, Docker, Microsoft Azure, Amazon Web Services

(AWS), CI/CD pipelines, Google

Education

2015 - 2019 Ph.D. in astrophysics (cosmology) at the University of Oslo, thesis tit-

led "Astrophysical Simulations for Uncovering Signatures of Gravity".

Supervisor: David F. Mota.

2013 - 2015 M.Sc. in Astronomy at the University of Oslo, thesis titled "Cosmolo-

gical Simulations with Disformally Coupled Symmetron Fields".

2010 - 2013 B.Sc. in Physics, Astronomy and Meteorology at the University of

Oslo. Several extra courses in informatics.

Professional experience

2019 -Consultant, Expert Analytics. Focus on physical understanding, data preparation, and data analysis. 2015 - 2019PhD student, University of Oslo. Developed and extended several pieces of high-performance parallel software for studying alternative theories of gravity. Collaborated in a highly international research field. $25\,\%$ teaching duty in bachelor level astronomy course, including development of software for the students. 2012 - 2015Four semesters as group teacher (Teaching Assistant) in different courses at UiO and HiO (now OsloMet). Subjects include mathematics, physics and informatics. I answered questions about programming and science concepts, as well as graded exams. 2013 - 201427 % position as mathematics teacher with responsibility for a class of VG1 mathematics students. Blackboard and powerpoint lectures, and helping students with exercises. Designing and grading tests. Final grading of students.

Languages

Norwegian Native
English Fluent
Polish Intermediate
French Basic

Personal skills

Analytical and Good ability to understand and break down a new problem in a logical creative way, and to provide creative solutions when needed. Modeling and Able to implement a physical model into computer code in an efficient data analysis way, while avoiding numerical problems. Developing custom tools to analyse the output and compare it with measurements. Audio data Experience with audio recording, editing and analysis. Both hardware and equipment and software. Intuitive and Not afraid to explore unknown problems and technology. Ability to get curious an overview and learn necessary material quickly. Communication Many years of experience in teaching science and programming. Good and teaching ability to understand and explain difficult concepts.

Some interests and hobbies

Sports and Weightlifting, yoga, hiking, skiing, golf

nature

Music Digital music editing, as well as several analog instruments including:

drums, guitar, sitar, piano and gong

Personal Personal development, learning and experiencing new things, traveling,

puzzles, cooking, cultivating friendships

expertanalytics.no

Extended descriptions of selected projects

Activity Audio Analytics for diagnosing generators and industrial machinery

Period 2020 - 2020

Role Architecture developer

Staffing Team of 10

Description This Statkraft project is aimed at detecting and diagnosing changes

in operation of hydro power generators through analysis of recorded audio. I had a key role in the installation of microphones, setup of edge compute equipment, and collection and organization of data. I contributed with several important ideas for the analysis, as well as development of several algorithms and frameworks used on the edge

computing device in the power plant.

Tools Python, Amazon Web Services, TimescaleDB, Docker, physical theory

(acoustics), edge computing

Activity Automation of physical systems based on weather forecast

Period 2019 - 2020 Role Lead developer Staffing Team of 4

Description A cloud based application for modelling and optimising an automated

industrial control system. The application can be accessed from a compatible system through a RESTful API; the cloud application performs a calculation based on online weather data and physical models, and returns the calculated optimal parameters for the automated system. I developed most of the physical model, and implemented the cloud based application from scratch. I was also responsible for assessing and minimising security risks, developing a complete testing pipeline,

as well as writing user documentation.

Tools Python, Azure Web App, Azure SQL, physical modelling (meteorology,

thermodynamics)

Activity Cosmological simulations with scalar fields

Period 2013 - 2019 Role Researcher Staffing Team of 3 Description

Together with my supervisors (David Mota and Claudio Llinares), I extended the freely available cosmological N-body code RAMSES to simulate an additional disformal scalar degree of freedom. This introduces a highly non-linear hyperbolic differential equation for the scalar field, as well as complex equations for the extra forces on the N-body particles. RAMSES is written in FORTRAN, and is designed to run in parallel on supercomputing clusters. Hence, I paid special attention to memory usage, efficient MPI parallelism, and low level code optimization. The output data ranged from gigabytes to terabytes, and statistical analysis of the output was necessary to draw scientific conclusions. I wrote several auxiliary tools for data and image analysis, as well as a 1-dimensional hyperbolic solver in spherical symmetry for more detailed study of the non-linear equation of motion of the scalar field.

Tools

Physical modeling, statistical data analysis, image analysis, scientific writing, FORTRAN, Python

Activity Development and use of student software: AST2000 Mission Control

Period 2015 - 2017

Role Developer and tester

Staffing Team of 8

Description As part of my work as a group teacher in AST1100/AST2000, I had

a leading role as developer of the Python backend that the students used for visualisation. The code procedurally generates a virtual solar system for each student, and during the course the student interacts with this code to launch a satellite from one planet, achieve orbit around another planet and land a landing module safely. After finishing development and writing the exercises and user manual, I had the main responsibility for updating the codebase when students reported bugs

and inconsistencies.

Tools Analytical modeling, procedural generation, user interfacing, pedago-

gical writing, Python, LaTeX